Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes.
A series of short videos that will quickly get
you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program.
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen.
Lesson 2 - Working with MuseScore
In this lesson, we’ll take a look at the
interface and get a general idea
of how things work in MuseScore
For the most part,
MuseScore uses a single window interface
At the top of the screen
are the redesigned menus
The toolbar at the top of the main window
contains commonly used tools
The top row starts with some basic File menu functions
and then the undo and redo buttons
Notice that tool tips appear
when you hover over an icon
The Zoom menu contains common settings
You can also use the shortcuts
to change the setting.
Oh and by the way, zooming does not affect print size
The View control lets us choose between standard
page view and the new continuous view
This is really useful for large scores
Next we have the Playback controls
a metronome
Concert Pitch
and the new Image Capture tool
You’ll find some of these can also be accessed
from menus or by using shortcuts
The second row of the toolbar contains
all of the note entry tools
We’ll be looking at note entry in the next lesson
You can customize the toolbar by right-clicking
and then selecting the items
that you would like displayed
All other entries are entered from the palettes on the left
As we did in the first lesson
click on a palette name
choose the item and just drag it to the score
Some of these items have shortcuts
and you can customize the shortcuts in the Preferences
A new feature is custom workspaces
There are two built-in workspaces,
Basic and Advanced
You can also create your own workspace
using either your favorite built-in palettes
or ones you create yourself.
The inspector is also new in this version
Click on any item in the score
and you’ll see its properties
You can hide items here,
change the appearance
or precisely adjust the location
Double-click the title bar of the inspector
or the palettes
and you create floating windows for them
Double-click the title bar again to redock them
The view menu contains other interface elements
The navigator makes it easy to move around
your score, particularly for larger scores
and the piano keyboard can make it easier
to enter notes when you don’t have
a MIDI keyboard available
Preferences are found in the
MuseScore menu on Mac OS
or under the Edit menu on Windows.
While MuseScore will run right out of the box,
it’s a good idea to know what’s here
We’ll take a look at this in a little more
depth a little later on
So now you should have a pretty good idea
where everything is in MuseScore
and should be ready to get down to work
In our next lesson,
we’ll look at note entry methods